Guide to the Taxi Rank and File Coalition Records WAG.139
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Taxi Rank and File Coalition Records
1956-1993
1971-1987
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Taxi Rank and File Coalition
Ravitz, Joyce
Zeiger, Henry
Seltzer, Steven
WAG.139
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Taxi Rank and File Coalition (TRFC), an organized group of disenchanted members of the New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036 was formed on April 15, 1971 in response to efforts by the leadership of the union and the taxi fleet owners to ratify a contract without a membership vote. For nearly seven years, the Coalition fought for a fair contract, better working conditions and a more democratic union. Members opposed what they saw as the autocracy of the founder of the union, Harry Van Arsdale, Jr. The materials in this collection include legal documents, flyers, newsletters, minutes, notes, press releases, correspondence, clippings, conference reports, health committee surveys and songbooks relating to the political and cultural activities of the Taxi Rank and File Coalition. Also included are some materials relating to Taxi Drivers Union Local 3036 and to successor organizations of the TRFC.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Scope and Content Note
The materials in this collection include legal documents, flyers, newsletters, minutes, notes, press releases, correspondence, clippings, conference reports, health committee surveys and songbooks relating to the political and cultural activities of the Taxi Rank and File Coalition. As members of the New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036, the Coalition ran in several shop and citywide elections to expand rank and file bargaining rights. The bulk of the materials focus on these campaigns and the subsequent legal battles against the entrenched union leadership and taxi fleet owners. In 1974, the Coalition openly espoused a radical ideology and a small number of materials reflect their emerging radicalization and encounters with outside taxi unions and socialist organizations around the country. The collection also includes financial records of Local 3036 and taxi Industry benefit funds and some papers of successor organizations, Taxi Workers against a Sellout and the Lease Drivers Defense Fund.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Organized into 1 series:
I, General Files, 1956-1993.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Taxi Rank and File Coalition (TRFC), an organized group of disenchanted members of the New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036 was formed on April 15, 1971 in response to efforts by the leadership of the union and the taxi fleet owners to ratify a contract without a membership vote. For nearly seven years, the Coalition fought for a fair contract, better working conditions and a more democratic union. Members opposed what they saw as the autocracy of the founder of the union, Harry Van Arsdale, Jr.
TRFC ran a full slate of candidates in the 1971 election, polling a consistent third of the vote throughout the city. In response to alleged corruption, the Coalition filed complaints of over thirty counts of fraud with the Department of Labor. In 1972, the union leadership agreed to binding arbitration of the 1970 contract without a ratification vote in direct violation of the union constitution. TRFC filed a federal lawsuit against the union leadership and won a 1974 court order guaranteeing membership certain rights in ratifying collective bargaining agreements. The union executive board illegally refused to hold elections for garage chairmen and committeemen in 1972 and 1973, claiming lack of funds. In 1974, after yearly appeals to the union leadership failed, TRFC presented 2,500 signatures for the restoration of the committee elections and won a favorable ruling in court. The subsequent elections were marred with irregularities. On May 14 and 15, 1974 TRFC led a strike at the Dover Garage for unfair dismissals. After the dismissed won their jobs back, TRFC fought the proposed fair hike of the Taxi Commission. The Coalition openly supported a radical ideology in the Hot Seat, and on the shop floor.
In addition to running shop elections and initiating several lawsuits against the union leadership, the Coalition focused on the internal development of their organization. TRFC established a health committee, conducted a research project into the history and economics of the industry and organized study groups on the history of the labor movement, focusing on issues pertinent to the industry, such as racism, leasing and gypsy cabs. They published a songbook of original taxi songs and developed a skit that members performed at taxi garages and demonstrations. Their newspaper, Hot Seat, ran for 44 issues with a peak circulation of 10,000.
In July of 1977, the Coalition failed to run a slate of candidates in the election and ended publication of the Hot Seat. As the size of the taxi industry fleet shrank, many members left the union to find work elsewhere and the Coalition ceased to function as a citywide organization. Members of TRFC expressed their regret for not achieving greater victories in the fight against the established leaders of the union and cited their frustrations and fatigue in the fight for a more democratic union. In the fall of 1979, Steve Seltzer and Henry Zeiger, former members of TRFC, organized a successor group, Taxi Workers against a Sellout (TWAS), which continued to oppose the union leadership by campainging their own slate of candidates in subsequent elections. TWAS filed a lawsuit against the union for violating the 1974 court order.
In 1978, the union transferred afflilation to the Service Employees International Union and became the Taxi Drivers and Allied Workers Union, Local 3036, SEIU.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Taxi Rank and File Coalition Oral History Collection (OH 013)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Joyce Ravitz and Henry Zeiger in 1991. Additional donations made by Steven Seltzer in 2001 and 2004. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1978.006, NPA.2000.259, and NPA.2001.078.
Taxicab drivers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor union democracy -- New York (State) -- New York.; Taxicab drivers -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036; Taxi Drivers and Allied Workers Union. Local 3036, SEIU; Seltzer, Steven; Taxi Rank and File Coalition; Van Arsdale, Harry, 1905-1986; United States. National Labor Relations Board; Zeiger, Henry; Ravitz, Joyce; Zeiger, Henry; Seltzer, Steven
- Series I, General Files, 1956-1993.
  - Ann Service Garage, undated; 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arbitration: Dover Garage II and New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036, et al.: Grievances, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arbitration: Metropolitan Taxicab Board of Trade and New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036: Safety Check, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arbitration: New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036 and Metropolitan Taxicab Board of Trade: Disciplinary Action and Termination, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arbitration: New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036 and Metropolitan Taxicab Board of Trade: Lease Arrangements, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arbitration: New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036 and Metropolitan Taxicab Board of Trade: Shift Extensions, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Back Bay Taxi Drivers Association (Boston, MA), 1974; 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bargaining, undated; 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bargaining, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bargaining, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bargaining (I), 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bargaining (II), 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bargaining, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bargaining, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bargaining: Arbitration: Award for Contract, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Butler Garage, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - CFC: Centers for Change Newsletter (with taxi article), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, undated; 1970-1975; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clippings: Pensions, undated; 1978; 1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Clippings: Service Employees International Union, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Clippings: Strike, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Coalition of Arlington Taxidrivers (Virginia): Newsletters, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Coalition of Labor Union Women (CLUW), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Conference: Cultural Workshop, Jan 11, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Conference: Hard Times, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Conference: Minis, Spring 1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Conference: Organization, May 5, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Conference: Rank and File Program, Nov 3, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Conference: Retreat, Summer 1976 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Conference: Strategy, Feb 12, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Constitution (New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036), 1966-1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Constitution (Taxi Drivers and Allied Workers Union, Local 3036, SEIU), 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Constitution: Amendments, 1970-1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Constitution: Clippings, 1967-1978 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Cooper Square Development Committee, 1965-1966; 1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence: General, undated; 1972-1983 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence: Hot Seat (Newsletter), undated; 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Cruising Ban, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cultural Activities: Proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Dover Garage, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Dover Garage: Questionnaires, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Drivers Solidarity Coalition (San Francisco, CA), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Elections, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Elections, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Elections, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Elections, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Elections, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Elections, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Elections, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Elections (I), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Elections (II), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Elections, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Elections, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Elections: Arbitration: Certification of Results, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Elections: Arbitration: Thomas Iandoli - Charles Petses Slate, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Elections: Clippings, 1974-1989 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Endorsements, undated; 1978; 1980; 1982 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Fare Hikes, 1964; 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Fare Hikes: Clippings, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Finances (New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036), 1969-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Finances: Annual Reports (New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036), 1967-1988; 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Finances: Annuity Plan (New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036), 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Finances: General Fund Statements (New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036), 1966-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Finances: Taxicab Industry Health and Welfare Fund, 1977-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Finances: Taxicab Industry Pension Fund, 1966-1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Finances: Taxicab Industry Pension Fund Reports, 1974; 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Finances: Taxicab Industry Pension Fund Reports, 1983-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Finances: Taxicab Industry Scholarship Fund, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Finances: Taxicab Industry Training and Educational Fund, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Finances: Taxicab Industry Vacation Fund, 1974; 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fleetworkers Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Flyers, 1970-1978 (Box Shared Tamiment OS004, Box 2, Folder 15)
  - General Membership Meeting (New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036), 1972;1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Grievances, undated; 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Guild of Taxi Drivers and Associated Workers (Minneapolis, MN), 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Gypsies, 1969-1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Health Committee: Health Tests, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - History: Taxi Organizing, undated; 1971; 1973; 1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Hodgson, James; Secretary of Labor v. New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036, 1969; 1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Independent Drivers Association (Denver, CO), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - International Brotherhood of Teamsters: Taxi Organizing, undated; 1956; 1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - International Socialists: David Katz Article on Taxi Wildcat, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Lease Drivers Defense Fund (I), 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Lease Drivers Defense Fund (II), 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Leasing, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - March 2nd Coalition: Planning Meeting, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - May Day Events, 1973; 1975 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Minutes: Membership and Steering Committee, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - National Caucus of Labor Committees, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - National Labor Relations Board: Complaint of John Gordan v. Dover Garage II, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - National Labor Relations Board: Complaint of Judith Balchan and Steven Seltzer v. Metropolitan Taxicab Board of Trade, et al., 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - National Labor Relations Board: Complaint of William Orleans v. Columbia Operating Co., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - National Labor Relations Board: Complaints of Taxi Rank and File Coalition v. New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036 (I), 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - National Labor Relations Board: Complaints of Taxi Rank and File Coalition v. New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036 (II), 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - National Labor Relations Board: Various Cases, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036: Correspondence, 1972-1973; 1982 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036: Flyers and Bulletins, 1971-1976 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Newark Airport Cab Driver's Bulletin, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Newsletters (Taxi), 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Newsletters: Down at Dover, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Newsletters: Fare Share (Ann Garage), 1971-1972; 1976 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Newsletters: Hot Seat, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Newsletters: Trafic (Taxi Rank and File Internal Communication), 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - November 4 Coalition, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Oral History Project: Guidelines, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Paladino, Angelo v. Taxicab Industry Pension Fund, et al., 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Petitions, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Petses, Charles; New York City Taxi Drivers Union, Local 3036 Vice President: Assault on, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Port Authority of New York and New Jersey: Dispatchers, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Position Papers and Proposals, 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Press Releases, undated; 1971-1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Put the Bosses on the Street, Let the Workers Run the Fleets" (Draft flyer), undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Queens Forest Coalition of Concerned Drivers, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Questionnaires (Iota Garage; Cab Trans), 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Racism: Statements and Articles, undated; 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Rules Governing Taxi Drivers and Public Coaches, 1962; 1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Safety, 1973-1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Shift Changes, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Song Books and Song Sheets, undated; 1973-1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Spartacist League, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Spector Cab Corp. and Metropolitan Taxicab Board of Trade v. The City of New York, et al., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "The Stillness of Taxicab #753" (Short story typescript), undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Study Group Reading Lists, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Syndicat National des Chauffeurs de Taxi de Montreal: Newsletters: Taxi, undated; 1974 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Taxi at the Crossroads: Which Way to Turn? (Taxi Rank and File Coalition pamphlet), undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Taxi Commission, 1971; 1973-1978 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Taxi Project, The Museum of Modern Art, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Taxi Rank and File Coalition, et al. v. Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., et al. (I), 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Taxi Rank and File Coalition, et al. v. Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., et al. (II), 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Taxi Rank and File Coalition, et al. v. Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., et al. (III), 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Taxi Rank and File Coalition, et al. v. Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., et al. (IV), 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Taxi Rank and File Coalition, et al. v. Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., et al.: Correspondence and Petitions, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Taxi Rank and File Coalition, et al. v. Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., et al.: Notes, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Taxi Rank and File Coalition, et al. v. Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., et al. (Request to Revise Settlement), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Taxi Rank and File Coalition, et al. v. Harry Van Arsdale, Jr., et al. (Request to Revise Settlement): Affidavits, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Taxi Workers against a Sellout, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Taxi Workers against a Sellout, et al. v. Ben Goldberg and Taxi Drivers and Allied Workers Union, Local 3036, SEIU, 1983; 1985 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Taxi Workers for a Democratic Union, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Taxi Workers for Decisive Action, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Taxicab Drivers Union, Local 156 (Philadelphia), 1973 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Taxicab Industry Local 3036 Benefit Fund, et al. v. Ann Service Corporation, et al., 1983 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Tenants Groups (including Metropolitan Council on Housing), undated; 1966; 1969-1971 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - United Jewish Appeal, Taxi Division, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - United Taxi Workers, undated; 1976 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Vietnam War, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Watch-Dog Committee (and New Watch-Dog Committee), 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - WBAI (discussion on Taxi Rank and File Coalition), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Welfare Fund: International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 237: New York City Audit Report on, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Wisconsin General and Industrial Workers Union, Local 104, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Women Taxi Drivers, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Workers Action Movement (Progressive Labor Party, Dick Sevrens), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Workers' League: Mechanics and Drivers for a Decent Contract, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Zarr, Edward v. Taxi Drivers and Allied Workers Union, Local 3036, SEIU, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Zeiger, Henry, et al. v. Ben Goldberg, et al., undated (Box 3, Folder 51)